Guide to the Kurt von Schuschnigg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kurt von Schuschnigg papers
1938-1947
MS 436
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Typescript of von Schuschnigg's prison memoir, Requiem in Rot-Weiss-Rot, with notes for changes for the English translation, Austrian Requiem.
Schuschnigg, Kurt, 1897-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edwin J. Beinecke in 1958 and 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Kurt von Schuschnigg was born December 14, 1897, at Riva (Gardasso). He was a lawyer and was elected to the Austrian national parliament as a Christian Socialist in 1927. He became Minister of Justice in 1932, and in May 1933 also became Minister of Education. After the assassination of Chancellor Dollfuss, he became Chancellor in July 1934. In the struggle against the German and Austrian Nazis he sought to maintain the existing authoritarian form of government of Dollfuss and the independence of Austria. He suppressed one major attempt by the Nazis to take over the country. Although his international allies deserted him, he sought to face Hitler alone and met with him at Berchtesgoden February 12, 1938. An ultimatum was presented by Hitler, but von Schuschnigg sought to forestall his move by declaring a plebecite to decide the Austrian-German question. He was frustrated in this attempt by the arrival of the German Army the day preceding the proposed plebecite.
Von Schuschnigg spent the war in prison waiting for a trial on charges by the Nazis. He came to the United States in 1945 and has been a professor of law in St. Louis since 1948.[1]
Among his works are: Dreimal Österreich (Vienna, 1937) [there are two translations of this under the title Farewell Austria and My Austria], Requiem in Rot-Weiss-Rot (Zurich, 1947) [the English translation of this is Austrian Requiem], and International Law: An Introduction to the law of peace(Milwaukee, 1959).
He died in 1977
[1] Der Grose Brockhaus, Vol. X, Wiesbaden, Germany (1956), p. 513.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the over 819 page typescript of Kurt von Schuschnigg's Requiem in Rot-Weiss-Rot (Zurich, 1947) which was published in an English translation by Trung von Hildebrand in the United States under the title, Austrian Requiem(New York, 1946). Of this book von Schuschnigg writes:
Most of this book was written between the summer of 1938 and the summer of 1945. During this time I was cut off from the world and knew little about world events- nor did I know what was to become of me. The book, therefore, cannot claim to be anything but a personal account and a human confession.
Parts of these writings were submitted chapter by chapter to the censorship of the Gestapo, or some of them were written... in order to avoid confiscation of everything I had written during my detention... I also wished to put my personal views on record, since neither the Gestapo nor the German government showed any interest in finding out the truth about my views or my activities... The greater part of the manuscript, however, was kept secret; not without difficulty, as my scant belongings were rigidly examined every time I was moved from one camp to another...
Later, during 1943, I was tempted more than once to destroy the entire work, or at least to revise what I had written so far. But finally most of it remained exactly as I had written it down during my detention...
[Kurt von Schuschnigg, Austrian Requiem, translated by Trung von Hildebrand, New York (1946), pp. viii-ix.]
The typescript is arranged in the box as von Schuschnigg originally numbered it. Massive changes were made, especially for the English edition. His list of changes is translated in the Description of the Series.
The papers were the gift of Edwin J. Beinecke in 1958 and 1964.
Fascism -- Austria; Austria -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Europe; Politicians; Public officers; Schuschnigg, Kurt, 1897-1977; Schuschnigg, Kurt, 1897-1977 ( Austrian Requiem); Schuschnigg, Kurt, 1897-1977 ( Requiem in Rot-Weiss-Rot)
- DESCRIPTION OF SERIES
  - Note from von Schuschnigg, Rome, 26 Feb. 1946, listing material sent for English translation, table of contents, list of changes, new titles. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Table of contents (the worn table of contents with the changes made listed made below)
  - List of changes (here translated)
    - I. Reductions
      - A. Completely removed.
        - Vol. I, Chapter 7 (Der autaritaere christliche Staat.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. I, Chapter 9 (Der versuchte, berufstaendische Aufbau) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. I, Chapter 10 (Bilanz) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. II, Chapter 16 (Préces meae non…) [the whole first section: Zur Psychologie eines Haeftlings] (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. II, Chapter 19 (Oro supplex…) [the section entitled "Palmsonntag,1939]" (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. II, Chapter 23 ("Dionysus und der…") (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. II, Chapter 24 ("Vox clamantis") (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - B. Further Reductions.
        - Vol. I, Chapter 3 ("Altoesterr. Suenden"): page 257, first 10 lines, from "Nicht weil er etwa…" to "Zeitrechnung begonnen hat." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 262, last 8 lines, from "Wiederum suchten…" (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 263, from "und tschechen setrenn hat." (next to last part) with the first three paragraphs of this page. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. I, Chapter 5 ("Vorboten des Umberuchs") (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 297: paragraphs 2,3,4. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 298: Paragraph 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 300: paragraphs 2,3. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - pages 310-304: completely removed. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 305: the first two lines and in the third line the number "4"/so that the text begins with "Natürlich war die lage..." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. I, Chapter 6 ("Die oesterreichische Wunden") (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 318: Paragraphs 2, 3 (from "Dass wir den Friedens. Vertrag…" to "…Nutzen ziehlen konnte." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. I, Chapter 8 (Der selbstaendige und freie Staat." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 347 paragraphs 1,2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 351 in the 8th sentence, 1 line from the top, the part: "…internationale anerk-annte Autoritaet war "change for internationale anerkannte Autoritaet ist." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 352: Remove 2nd paragraph (from "Beé dergegebenen…" to"…zu denhen gewaehnt gewaehnt was.") (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 357: Remove the two last words of the last line ("Es seè) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 358: Remove the first three paragraphs (from "…an seine Stelle getreben." (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Vol. II, Chapter 12 (Zeitenwende) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - page 542: 7 lines from the top should really read: "Wer aber-wie meine Freinde und ich-den gegenteiligen…" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - II. Insertions and Supplements
      - In the First Volume:
        - After the chapter "Auslandsreisen" and before the closing chapter of the first volume "Zeitenwende"-insert the new chapter (Die Beilage A)" Wenn und Abers, Eventualitaeten" (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - In the second volume:
        - In the former chapter 21: "Land in Sicht" insert as page 676a (161a)* the diary entries fron 9 December 1941. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - In the former chapter 15 "Mihi quoque opein dediste…" a part of the earlier text add the section marked Beilage B. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - In the former chapter 22: Oranienburges Tagebuch
          - a) insert as 785a (269a) Diary entries from 9 February 1945 (all entries from 8 Feb-12 Feb.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
          - b) insert new pages 788a (273) and 789a(274) (he then gives a list of things on these pages) (Box 1, Folder 1)
          - c) insert new pages 792a-792h (277-277g) these are the diary entries from 10, 12, 14, 15, 16, and 17 April. (Box 1, Folder 1)
          - d) insert new pages 798a to 804 (284-290) (Box 1, Folder 1)
          - e) A part of the earlier removed closing chapter should be inserted: "Lux aeterna… Ausklang." pp. 802-804 (288-290) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - *N.B.: The higher numbers refer to the case if the book is numbered consecutively in both volumes. In case the second volume is numbered starting again, the lower numbers apply. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of number of pages for various sections of the book.
    - Chapter I. Introduction. "Das ö sterreichische Drama.(Eine kulturhistorische Betrachtung.)" pp. 1-76. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chapter II. "Ein Gang durch die Dämmerung." pp. 77-253. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Note for part II; Chapter III. "Alt-österreichische Süden?" pp. 255-275 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapter IV. "Die erbliche Belastuny." pp. 276-287. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chapter V. "Verbaten des Umbruchs." pp. 288-314. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chapter VI. "Die österreichischen Wunden." pp. 315-331. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chapter VII. "Der autoritare, christliche Stast?" pp.332-346. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chapter VIII. "Der selbständige und freie Stast?" pp. 347-360 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chapter IX. "Der versuchte beruf-ständige Dufbou."pp.361-380 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chapter X. "Eine Bilang." pp. 381-394. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chapter XI. "Auslandreisen." pp. 395-535. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 1. Ungarn. pp 395-408 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 2. Italien, Florenz-Rom,-Ravenna-pp. 409-421. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 3. Geachichte und Gegenwart: Impressionen und Gespräche pp. 422-461. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 4. Genf. pp. 462-472. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 5. Paris-London. pp. 473-522. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 6. Prag. pp. 523-535. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Beilage "A" "Wenn und Aber, Eventuatitäten." (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Chapter XII. "Zeitenwende." pp. 536-544 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Forward to parts III and IV; (here begins Vo1.2 with a slightly different numbering system) Chapter XIV. "Quantus tremor est futurus..." pp. 522-534; Chapter XV. "Culpa rubet vultus mens..." pp.535-542. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chapter XVI. "Mihi quoque opem dedisti." pp. 543-554. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chapter XVII. "Preces meae non sunt lignae…" pp.555-566. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Chapter XVIII: "Inter oves locum praesta…" pp.567-577; Chapter XIX."Confutatis.maledictis…" pp. 577-599. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Chapter XX. "Oro supplex et acclines." pp. 600-617. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Chapter XXI. "Haic ergo parce Deus." pp. 618-628. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Part IV. Diary. 30 October 1939 to Christmas 1942, pp. 629-698. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Part IV. Diary. January 1943 to Christmas 1944, pp. 699-777. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Part.IV. Diary. January 1945 to 30 April 1949, pp.778-798. Conclusion. pp. 798a-819. (Box 1, Folder 23)